<?xml version='1.0'?> <!--*-nxml-*-->
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
        "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<refentry id="kdbus">

  <refentryinfo>
    <title>kdbus</title>
    <productname>kdbus</productname>
  </refentryinfo>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>kdbus</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>kdbus</refname>
    <refpurpose>Kernel Message Bus</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para>
      kdbus is an inter-process communication bus system controlled by the
      kernel. It provides user-space with an API to create buses and send
      unicast and multicast messages to one, or many, peers connected to the
      same bus. It does not enforce any layout on the transmitted data, but
      only provides the transport layer used for message interchange between
      peers.
    </para>
    <para>
      This set of man-pages gives a comprehensive overview of the kernel-level
      API, with all ioctl commands, associated structs and bit masks. However,
      most people will not use this API level directly, but rather let one of
      the high-level abstraction libraries help them integrate D-Bus
      functionality into their applications.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      kdbus provides a pseudo filesystem called <emphasis>kdbusfs</emphasis>,
      which is usually mounted on <filename>/sys/fs/kdbus</filename>. Bus
      primitives can be accessed as files and sub-directories underneath this
      mount-point. Any advanced operations are done via
      <function>ioctl()</function> on files created by
      <emphasis>kdbusfs</emphasis>. Multiple mount-points of
      <emphasis>kdbusfs</emphasis> are independent of each other. This allows
      namespacing of kdbus by mounting a new instance of
      <emphasis>kdbusfs</emphasis> in a new mount-namespace. kdbus calls these
      mount instances domains and each bus belongs to exactly one domain.
    </para>

    <para>
      kdbus was designed as a transport layer for D-Bus, but is in no way
      limited, nor controlled by the D-Bus protocol specification. The D-Bus
      protocol is one possible application layer on top of kdbus.
    </para>

    <para>
      For the general D-Bus protocol specification, its payload format, its
      marshaling, and its communication semantics, please refer to the
      <ulink url="http://dbus.freedesktop.org/doc/dbus-specification.html">
      D-Bus specification</ulink>.
    </para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Terminology</title>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Domain</title>
      <para>
        A domain is a <emphasis>kdbusfs</emphasis> mount-point containing all
        the bus primitives. Each domain is independent, and separate domains
        do not affect each other.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Bus</title>
      <para>
        A bus is a named object inside a domain. Clients exchange messages
        over a bus. Multiple buses themselves have no connection to each other;
        messages can only be exchanged on the same bus. The default endpoint of
        a bus, to which clients establish connections, is the "bus" file
        /sys/fs/kdbus/&lt;bus name&gt;/bus.
        Common operating system setups create one "system bus" per system,
        and one "user bus" for every logged-in user. Applications or services
        may create their own private buses. The kernel driver does not
        distinguish between different bus types, they are all handled the same
        way. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.bus</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Endpoint</title>
      <para>
        An endpoint provides a file to talk to a bus. Opening an endpoint
        creates a new connection to the bus to which the endpoint belongs. All
        endpoints have unique names and are accessible as files underneath the
        directory of a bus, e.g., /sys/fs/kdbus/&lt;bus&gt;/&lt;endpoint&gt;
        Every bus has a default endpoint called "bus".
        A bus can optionally offer additional endpoints with custom names
        to provide restricted access to the bus. Custom endpoints carry
        additional policy which can be used to create sandboxes with
        locked-down, limited, filtered access to a bus. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.endpoint</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Connection</title>
      <para>
        A connection to a bus is created by opening an endpoint file of a
        bus. Every ordinary client connection has a unique identifier on the
        bus and can address messages to every other connection on the same
        bus by using the peer's connection ID as the destination. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.connection</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Pool</title>
      <para>
        Each connection allocates a piece of shmem-backed memory that is
        used to receive messages and answers to ioctl commands from the kernel.
        It is never used to send anything to the kernel. In order to access that
        memory, an application must mmap() it into its address space. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.pool</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Well-known Name</title>
      <para>
        A connection can, in addition to its implicit unique connection ID,
        request the ownership of a textual well-known name. Well-known names are
        noted in reverse-domain notation, such as com.example.service1. A
        connection that offers a service on a bus is usually reached by its
        well-known name. An analogy of connection ID and well-known name is an
        IP address and a DNS name associated with that address. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.name</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Message</title>
      <para>
        Connections can exchange messages with other connections by addressing
        the peers with their connection ID or well-known name. A message
        consists of a message header with information on how to route the
        message, and the message payload, which is a logical byte stream of
        arbitrary size. Messages can carry additional file descriptors to be
        passed from one connection to another, just like passing file
        descriptors over UNIX domain sockets. Every connection can specify which
        set of metadata the kernel should attach to the message when it is
        delivered to the receiving connection. Metadata contains information
        like: system time stamps, UID, GID, TID, proc-starttime, well-known
        names, process comm, process exe, process argv, cgroup, capabilities,
        seclabel, audit session, loginuid and the connection's human-readable
        name. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.message</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Item</title>
      <para>
        The API of kdbus implements the notion of items, submitted through and
        returned by most ioctls, and stored inside data structures in the
        connection's pool. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.item</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Broadcast, signal, filter, match</title>
      <para>
        Signals are messages that a receiver opts in for by installing a blob of
        bytes, called a 'match'. Signal messages must always carry a
        counter-part blob, called a 'filter', and signals are only delivered to
        peers which have a match that white-lists the message's filter. Senders
        of signal messages can use either a single connection ID as receiver,
        or the special connection ID
        <constant>KDBUS_DST_ID_BROADCAST</constant> to potentially send it to
        all connections of a bus, following the logic described above. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.match</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        and
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.message</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Policy</title>
      <para>
        A policy is a set of rules that define which connections can see, talk
        to, or register a well-known name on the bus. A policy is attached to
        buses and custom endpoints, and modified by policy holder connections or
        owners of custom endpoints. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.policy</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Privileged bus users</title>
      <para>
        A user connecting to the bus is considered privileged if it is either
        the creator of the bus, or if it has the CAP_IPC_OWNER capability flag
        set. See
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.connection</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for more details.
      </para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Bus Layout</title>

    <para>
      A <emphasis>bus</emphasis> provides and defines an environment that peers
      can connect to for message interchange. A bus is created via the kdbus
      control interface and can be modified by the bus creator. It applies the
      policy that control all bus operations. The bus creator itself does not
      participate as a peer. To establish a peer
      <emphasis>connection</emphasis>, you have to open one of the
      <emphasis>endpoints</emphasis> of a bus. Each bus provides a default
      endpoint, but further endpoints can be created on-demand. Endpoints are
      used to apply additional policies for all connections on this endpoint.
      Thus, they provide additional filters to further restrict access of
      specific connections to the bus.
    </para>

    <para>
      Following, you can see an example bus layout:
    </para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[
                                  Bus Creator
                                       |
                                       |
                                    +-----+
                                    | Bus |
                                    +-----+
                                       |
                    __________________/ \__________________
                   /                                       \
                   |                                       |
             +----------+                             +----------+
             | Endpoint |                             | Endpoint |
             +----------+                             +----------+
         _________/|\_________                   _________/|\_________
        /          |          \                 /          |          \
        |          |          |                 |          |          |
        |          |          |                 |          |          |
   Connection  Connection  Connection      Connection  Connection  Connection
    ]]></programlisting>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Data structures and interconnections</title>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
  +--------------------------------------------------------------------------+
  | Domain (Mount Point)                                                     |
  | /sys/fs/kdbus/control                                                    |
  | +----------------------------------------------------------------------+ |
  | | Bus (System Bus)                                                     | |
  | | /sys/fs/kdbus/0-system/                                              | |
  | | +-------------------------------+ +--------------------------------+ | |
  | | | Endpoint                      | | Endpoint                       | | |
  | | | /sys/fs/kdbus/0-system/bus    | | /sys/fs/kdbus/0-system/ep.app  | | |
  | | +-------------------------------+ +--------------------------------+ | |
  | | +--------------+ +--------------+ +--------------+ +---------------+ | |
  | | | Connection   | | Connection   | | Connection   | | Connection    | | |
  | | | :1.22        | | :1.25        | | :1.55        | | :1.81         | | |
  | | +--------------+ +--------------+ +--------------+ +---------------+ | |
  | +----------------------------------------------------------------------+ |
  |                                                                          |
  | +----------------------------------------------------------------------+ |
  | | Bus (User Bus for UID 2702)                                          | |
  | | /sys/fs/kdbus/2702-user/                                             | |
  | | +-------------------------------+ +--------------------------------+ | |
  | | | Endpoint                      | | Endpoint                       | | |
  | | | /sys/fs/kdbus/2702-user/bus   | | /sys/fs/kdbus/2702-user/ep.app | | |
  | | +-------------------------------+ +--------------------------------+ | |
  | | +--------------+ +--------------+ +--------------+ +---------------+ | |
  | | | Connection   | | Connection   | | Connection   | | Connection    | | |
  | | | :1.22        | | :1.25        | | :1.55        | | :1.81         | | |
  | | +--------------+ +--------------+ +--------------------------------+ | |
  | +----------------------------------------------------------------------+ |
  +--------------------------------------------------------------------------+
    ]]></programlisting>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Metadata</title>

    <refsect2>
      <title>When metadata is collected</title>
      <para>
        kdbus records data about the system in certain situations. Such metadata
        can refer to the currently active process (creds, PIDs, current user
        groups, process names and its executable path, cgroup membership,
        capabilities, security label and audit information), connection
        information (description string, currently owned names) and time stamps.
      </para>
      <para>
        Metadata is collected at the following times.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          When a bus is created (<constant>KDBUS_CMD_MAKE</constant>),
          information about the calling task is collected. This data is returned
          by the kernel via the <constant>KDBUS_CMD_BUS_CREATOR_INFO</constant>
          call.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            When a connection is created (<constant>KDBUS_CMD_HELLO</constant>),
            information about the calling task is collected. Alternatively, a
            privileged connection may provide 'faked' information about
            credentials, PIDs and security labels which will be stored instead.
            This data is returned by the kernel as information on a connection
            (<constant>KDBUS_CMD_CONN_INFO</constant>). Only metadata that a
            connection allowed to be sent (by setting its bit in
            <varname>attach_flags_send</varname>) will be exported in this way.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            When a message is sent (<constant>KDBUS_CMD_SEND</constant>),
            information about the sending task and the sending connection are
            collected. This metadata will be attached to the message when it
            arrives in the receiver's pool. If the connection sending the
            message installed faked credentials (see
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.connection</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>),
            the message will not be augmented by any information about the
            currently sending task. Note that only metadata that was requested
            by the receiving connection will be collected and attached to
            messages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        Which metadata items are actually delivered depends on the following
        sets and masks:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          (a) the system-wide kmod creds mask
          (module parameter <varname>attach_flags_mask</varname>)
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          (b) the per-connection send creds mask, set by the connecting client
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          (c) the per-connection receive creds mask, set by the connecting
          client
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          (d) the per-bus minimal creds mask, set by the bus creator
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          (e) the per-bus owner creds mask, set by the bus creator
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          (f) the mask specified when querying creds of a bus peer
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          (g) the mask specified when querying creds of a bus owner
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        With the following rules:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            [1] The creds attached to messages are determined as
            <constant>a &amp; b &amp; c</constant>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            [2] When connecting to a bus (<constant>KDBUS_CMD_HELLO</constant>),
            and <constant>~b &amp; d != 0</constant>, the call will fail with,
            <errorcode>-1</errorcode>, and <varname>errno</varname> is set to
            <constant>ECONNREFUSED</constant>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            [3] When querying creds of a bus peer, the creds returned are
            <constant>a &amp; b &amp; f</constant>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            [4] When querying creds of a bus owner, the creds returned are
            <constant>a &amp; e &amp; g</constant>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        Hence, programs might not always get all requested metadata items that
        it requested. Code must be written so that it can cope with this fact.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Benefits and heads-up</title>
      <para>
        Attaching metadata to messages has two major benefits.

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Metadata attached to messages is gathered at the moment when the
              other side calls <constant>KDBUS_CMD_SEND</constant>, or,
              respectively, then the kernel notification is generated. There is
              no need for the receiving peer to retrieve information about the
              task in a second step. This closes a race gap that would otherwise
              be inherent.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              As metadata is delivered along with messages in the same data
              blob, no extra calls to kernel functions etc. are needed to gather
              them.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        Note, however, that collecting metadata does come at a price for
        performance, so developers should carefully assess which metadata to
        really opt-in for. For best practice, data that is not needed as part
        of a message should not be requested by the connection in the first
        place (see <varname>attach_flags_recv</varname> in
        <constant>KDBUS_CMD_HELLO</constant>).
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Attach flags for metadata items</title>
      <para>
        To let the kernel know which metadata information to attach as items
        to the aforementioned commands, it uses a bitmask. In those, the
        following <emphasis>attach flags</emphasis> are currently supported.
        Both the the <varname>attach_flags_recv</varname> and
        <varname>attach_flags_send</varname> fields of
        <type>struct kdbus_cmd_hello</type>, as well as the payload of the
        <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_ATTACH_FLAGS_SEND</constant> and
        <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_ATTACH_FLAGS_RECV</constant> items follow this
        scheme.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_TIMESTAMP</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_TIMESTAMP</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_CREDS</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_CREDS</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_PIDS</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_PIDS</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_AUXGROUPS</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_AUXGROUPS</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_NAMES</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_OWNED_NAME</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_TID_COMM</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_TID_COMM</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_PID_COMM</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_PID_COMM</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_EXE</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_EXE</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_CMDLINE</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_CMDLINE</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_CGROUP</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_CGROUP</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_CAPS</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_CAPS</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_SECLABEL</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_SECLABEL</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_AUDIT</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_AUDIT</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><constant>KDBUS_ATTACH_CONN_DESCRIPTION</constant></term>
            <listitem><para>
              Requests the attachment of an item of type
              <constant>KDBUS_ITEM_CONN_DESCRIPTION</constant>.
            </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>
        Please refer to
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.item</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        for detailed information about the layout and payload of items and
        what metadata should be used to.
      </para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>The ioctl interface</title>

    <para>
      As stated in the 'synopsis' section above, application developers are
      strongly encouraged to use kdbus through one of the high-level D-Bus
      abstraction libraries, rather than using the low-level API directly.
    </para>

    <para>
      kdbus on the kernel level exposes its functions exclusively through
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>ioctl</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,
      employed on file descriptors returned by
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>open</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>
      on pseudo files exposed by
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>kdbus.fs</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Following is a list of all the ioctls, along with the command structs
      they must be used with.
    </para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="3" colsep="1">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>ioctl signature</entry>
            <entry>command</entry>
            <entry>transported struct</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><constant>0x40189500</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_BUS_MAKE</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x40189510</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_ENDPOINT_MAKE</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0xc0609580</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_HELLO</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd_hello *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x40189582</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_BYEBYE</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x40389590</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_SEND</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd_send *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x80409591</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_RECV</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd_recv *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x40209583</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_FREE</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd_free *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x401895a0</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_NAME_ACQUIRE</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x401895a1</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_NAME_RELEASE</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x80289586</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_LIST</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd_list *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x80309584</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_CONN_INFO</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd_info *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x40209551</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_UPDATE</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x80309585</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_BUS_CREATOR_INFO</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd_info *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x40189511</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_ENDPOINT_UPDATE</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x402095b0</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_MATCH_ADD</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd_match *</type></entry>
          </row><row>
            <entry><constant>0x402095b1</constant></entry>
            <entry><constant>KDBUS_CMD_MATCH_REMOVE</constant></entry>
            <entry><type>struct kdbus_cmd_match *</type></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      Depending on the type of <emphasis>kdbusfs</emphasis> node that was
      opened and what ioctls have been executed on a file descriptor before,
      a different sub-set of ioctl commands is allowed.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          On a file descriptor resulting from opening a
          <emphasis>control node</emphasis>, only the
          <constant>KDBUS_CMD_BUS_MAKE</constant> ioctl may be executed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          On a file descriptor resulting from opening a
          <emphasis>bus endpoint node</emphasis>, only the
          <constant>KDBUS_CMD_ENDPOINT_MAKE</constant> and
          <constant>KDBUS_CMD_HELLO</constant> ioctls may be executed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A file descriptor that was used to create a bus
          (via <constant>KDBUS_CMD_BUS_MAKE</constant>) is called a
          <emphasis>bus owner</emphasis> file descriptor. The bus will be
          active as long as the file descriptor is kept open.
          A bus owner file descriptor can not be used to
          employ any further ioctls. As soon as
          <citerefentry>
            <refentrytitle>close</refentrytitle>
            <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
          </citerefentry>
          is called on it, the bus will be shut down, along will all associated
          endpoints and connections. See
          <citerefentry>
            <refentrytitle>kdbus.bus</refentrytitle>
            <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
          </citerefentry>
          for more details.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A file descriptor that was used to create an endpoint
          (via <constant>KDBUS_CMD_ENDPOINT_MAKE</constant>) is called an
          <emphasis>endpoint owner</emphasis> file descriptor. The endpoint
          will be active as long as the file descriptor is kept open.
          An endpoint owner file descriptor can only be used
          to update details of an endpoint through the
          <constant>KDBUS_CMD_ENDPOINT_UPDATE</constant> ioctl. As soon as
          <citerefentry>
            <refentrytitle>close</refentrytitle>
            <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
          </citerefentry>
          is called on it, the endpoint will be removed from the bus, and all
          connections that are connected to the bus through it are shut down.
          See
          <citerefentry>
            <refentrytitle>kdbus.endpoint</refentrytitle>
            <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
          </citerefentry>
          for more details.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A file descriptor that was used to create a connection
          (via <constant>KDBUS_CMD_HELLO</constant>) is called a
          <emphasis>connection owner</emphasis> file descriptor. The connection
          will be active as long as the file descriptor is kept open.
          A connection owner file descriptor may be used to
          issue any of the following ioctls.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_UPDATE</constant> to tweak details of the
            connection. See
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.connection</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_BYEBYE</constant> to shut down a connection
            without losing messages. See
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.connection</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_FREE</constant> to free a slice of memory in
            the pool. See
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.pool</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_CONN_INFO</constant> to retrieve information
            on other connections on the bus. See
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.connection</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_BUS_CREATOR_INFO</constant> to retrieve
            information on the bus creator. See
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.connection</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_LIST</constant> to retrieve a list of
            currently active well-known names and unique IDs on the bus. See
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.name</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_SEND</constant> and
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_RECV</constant> to send or receive a message.
            See
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.message</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_NAME_ACQUIRE</constant> and
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_NAME_RELEASE</constant> to acquire or release
            a well-known name on the bus. See
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.name</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_MATCH_ADD</constant> and
            <constant>KDBUS_CMD_MATCH_REMOVE</constant> to add or remove
            a match for signal messages. See
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>kdbus.match</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
          </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      These ioctls, along with the structs they transport, are explained in
      detail in the other documents linked to in the 'see also' section below.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <simplelist type="inline">
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.bus</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.connection</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.endpoint</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.fs</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.item</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.message</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.name</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>kdbus.pool</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>ioctl</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>mmap</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>open</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>close</refentrytitle>
          <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
      </member>
      <member>
        <ulink url="http://freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/dbus">D-Bus</ulink>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
  </refsect1>

</refentry>
